<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Justice | WyoFile</title>
	<atom:link href="https://wyofile.com/category/justice/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://wyofile.com/category/justice/</link>
	<description>Indepth News about Wyoming People, Places &#38; Policy. Wyoming news.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2025 19:38:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/cropped-wyofile-icon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Justice | WyoFile</title>
	<link>https://wyofile.com/category/justice/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">74384313</site>	<item>
		<title>Wrongful death suit challenges Thermopolis cop for illegally entering home</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/wrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/wrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andrew Graham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 10:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law enforcement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mcdonalds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[methamphetamine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[michael mascorro]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[police shooting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Thermopolis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=113692</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="164" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.05%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=300%2C164&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="558" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.05%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=1024%2C558&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>The family of a man killed in a shootout with a Thermopolis police officer who busted into his home over a misdemeanor sued in federal court.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/wrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home/">Wrongful death suit challenges Thermopolis cop for illegally entering home</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="164" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.05%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=300%2C164&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="558" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.05%E2%80%AFAM.png?fit=1024%2C558&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home%2F&amp;linkname=Wrongful%20death%20suit%20challenges%20Thermopolis%20cop%20for%20illegally%20entering%20home" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home%2F&amp;linkname=Wrongful%20death%20suit%20challenges%20Thermopolis%20cop%20for%20illegally%20entering%20home" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home%2F&amp;linkname=Wrongful%20death%20suit%20challenges%20Thermopolis%20cop%20for%20illegally%20entering%20home" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home%2F&amp;linkname=Wrongful%20death%20suit%20challenges%20Thermopolis%20cop%20for%20illegally%20entering%20home" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home%2F&amp;linkname=Wrongful%20death%20suit%20challenges%20Thermopolis%20cop%20for%20illegally%20entering%20home" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home%2F&#038;title=Wrongful%20death%20suit%20challenges%20Thermopolis%20cop%20for%20illegally%20entering%20home" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/wrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home/" data-a2a-title="Wrongful death suit challenges Thermopolis cop for illegally entering home"></a></p>
<p>The first police killing in the town of Thermopolis’ history started with an investigation into methamphetamine use by workers at a local McDonald’s.</p>



<p>It ended with a bloody, close-range shootout inside a trailer home after an officer shouldered his way inside without a warrant. The officer, Sgt. Michael Mascorro, suffered a gunshot wound that came harrowingly close to killing him. While bleeding profusely, Mascorro shot and killed McDonald’s employee Buck Laramore.</p>



<p>Though Laramore shot first, wounding Mascorro while the officer’s gun was still in his holster, his mother and widow sued the Thermopolis Police Department in the U.S. District Court of Wyoming this week. They allege Mascorro had no grounds to enter the trailer and that Laramore was defending himself against a police officer who was, in essence, a lawless intruder into his home.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“This was a completely avoidable incident,” Sweetwater County District Attorney Dan Erramouspe wrote at the time, <a href="https://www.thermopir.com/story/2023/10/12/news/mascorro-cleared-in-fatal-shooting-but-is-found-to-have-illegally-broke-into-home/13897.html">according to the Thermopolis Independent Record</a>. The prosecutor, who conducted a criminal review of the shooting and is not involved in the civil lawsuit, ruled Mascorro entered Laramore&#8217;s home illegally. Town officials later rejected that conclusion.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In their lawsuit, Laramore’s relatives cite self-defense laws like Wyoming’s controversial “stand your ground” statute and the castle doctrine, both of which generally allow homeowners to protect themselves with deadly force from an intruder. While Erramouspe found Mascorro had entered the home illegally, the prosecutor also found he was justified in shooting back at Laramore. The state’s castle doctrine carries an exception for when the intruder in one’s home is a police officer, and when the shooting started, Mascorro was defending himself, the prosecutor wrote.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The family’s lawyers disagree. “It was Mascorro’s own reckless and deliberate conduct that unreasonably created his use of force,” they wrote in the complaint.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Neither lawyers for the plaintiffs nor Thermopolis Police Chief Pat Cornwall responded to messages from WyoFile this week seeking comment on the case.&nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Investigation</h4>



<p>The violence on April 28, 2023 can be traced back to two days earlier, when a different Thermopolis police officer arrested a different McDonald’s employee who had an outstanding warrant. When the officer helped that employee out of her patrol car at the jail, she found a glass pipe on the car seat, according to a report on the shooting compiled by Wyoming Division of Criminal Investigation agents. The employee had smoked meth from the pipe that morning with one of his McDonald’s colleagues, he told the officer.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Thermopolis police officers decided to contact the area health inspector, Jamie George, for a combined investigation into meth use among the McDonald’s employees. That investigation led Mascorro and a Hot Springs County sheriff’s deputy with a drug dog to the restaurant on April 28 — where Laramore had just started his work shift.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mascorro found Laramore suspicious. He saw Laramore leave the men’s room, and soon afterward the drug dog detected meth hidden in containers in the bathroom’s baby changing station, according to the DCI investigation. The officer asked Laramore to take a drug test, which the McDonald’s worker declined to do. When Mascorro asked for his name, Laramore misspelled it by one letter. He also said his birth year was 1988, when it was in fact 1989.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="732" height="1024" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?resize=732%2C1024&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-113682" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?resize=732%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 732w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?resize=214%2C300&amp;ssl=1 214w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?resize=768%2C1075&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?resize=1098%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 1098w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?resize=1200%2C1679&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?resize=780%2C1092&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?resize=400%2C560&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro.jpg?w=1372&amp;ssl=1 1372w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Mascorro-732x1024.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="(max-width: 732px) 100vw, 732px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sgt. Michael Mascorro poses for a photograph posted to the Thermopolis Police Department website. (Thermopolis Police Department)</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Laramore left the McDonald’s shortly after the exchange and returned home. When Mascorro learned Laramore had given him a misspelled name and the wrong birth year, he called a Hot Springs County prosecutor, according to an interview with the prosecutor conducted by the DCI investigators.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Kelly Owens, the prosecutor, told Mascorro they could not connect Laramore to the meth in the bathroom. The officer then said he wanted to arrest Laramore for interfering with the investigation by giving false information about himself. Owens suggested Mascorro could just write Laramore a ticket instead, according to the lawsuit. </p>



<p>But Mascorro wanted to arrest Laramore, he would later tell DCI agents. </p>



<p>A two-decade veteran of the U.S. Air Force, Mascorro had joined the Thermopolis Police Department eight years prior. At the time of the shooting, he was the agency’s second in command. The DCI agents who investigated Laramore’s death asked Mascorro why he went to Laramore’s home alone. The small police department was shorthanded, Mascorro told the investigators, and he did not have an option for backup. “It’s the nature of this job,” he said, according to the DCI report.&nbsp;</p>



<p>During his tenure in Thermopolis, Mascorro had received four use-of-force complaints, according to the lawsuit. He was accused of kicking a man and knocking him to the ground while arresting him, and in another instance, of escalating an encounter into a fight at Thermopolis’s signature drinking establishment, the One-Eyed Buffalo. Just six days before the shootout, the Wyoming Peace Officer Standards and Training Commission had cleared Mascorro of any wrongdoing in those incidents.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The lawsuit claims the department should have corrected aggressive behavior by Mascorro, and that doing so may have prevented the fatal shootout.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Laramore’s McDonald’s colleagues described him to DCI agents as a “big-hearted” and good worker who sometimes felt down about life. When agents asked one colleague if Laramore was suicidal, she told them he would never kill himself because of his love for his wife.&nbsp;</p>



<p>According to the DCI report, however, Mascorro learned from his dispatcher on his way to Laramore’s home that the man also had a record of assault charges. Laramore was well armed — DCI agents would recover three pistols when they searched the home after the shooting. Agents also found meth, fentanyl and marijuana.</p>



<p>Mascorro arrived on Laramore’s doorstep several hours after their first encounter at the McDonald’s, according to the DCI investigation. He banged on the door, which Laramore came to but did not exit. A storm door separated the two men as they spoke. Mascorro told Laramore to come outside so he could be arrested for interference. Laramore said he would not do so.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The situation would go “one of two ways,” Mascorro suggested, according to the lawsuit. Either Laramore would step outside, or Mascorro would “break the door in.”</p>



<p>Laramore closed the door of his home. Mascorro opened the storm door and began to ram the main door with his shoulder.&nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Shootout</strong> </h4>



<p>The Thermopolis Police Department released selective portions of Mascorro’s body camera footage from the incident, accompanying the footage with narration that gives the law enforcement view of the encounter. Mascorro entered the trailer because he believed Laramore could flee out the back door, the narration suggests.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In his interview with DCI, Mascorro said he considered Laramore’s closing of the door in his face the equivalent of fleeing arrest, and felt if he left to secure a warrant, Laramore would be gone when he returned.</p>



<p>In the lawsuit, the Laramore family’s attorneys argue Buck Laramore couldn’t have destroyed any evidence in the interference case because he had already given Mascorro the false information. There was no threat to the officer’s safety when the two men talked in the doorway, and Laramore’s refusal to step outside was not a crime, the complaint argued.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Laramore’s wife, Brandi, was also home.&nbsp;</p>



<p>When Mascorro broke through the door, he found Laramore standing in a hallway, pointing a Smith &amp; Wesson handgun at him with both hands.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="479" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=780%2C479&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-113674" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=1024%2C629&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=300%2C184&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=768%2C472&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=1200%2C737&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=780%2C479&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=400%2C246&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM.png?w=1400&amp;ssl=1 1400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.30.44%E2%80%AFAM-1024x629.png?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">
A screenshot from Sgt. Michael Mascorro’s body-worn camera footage is imprinted with narration from the Thermopolis Police Department. Buck Laramore stands in the lower right corner pointing his .45-caliber pistol at Mascorro. The officer broke into the home in April 2023 without a warrant and the two men shot each other. Laramore died. (Thermopolis Police Department footage)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Mascorro’s gun was still in its holster, according to the DCI report. Laramore fired once and put a .45-caliber bullet through Mascorro’s right arm and into his chest, where it broke one of the officer’s ribs and passed through his lung, narrowly missing his spine.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The shot knocked Mascorro to the ground.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Laramore advanced toward him, and according to the DCI report, likely fired another shot, though it didn’t strike Mascorro and it’s unclear where the round went.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Lying on the ground, Mascorro called on Laramore to “stop, stop.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>According to the lawsuit, Laramore did not fire another shot.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mascorro told the DCI agents he did not know why Laramore did not shoot him again, in the head, while he lay on the ground. But Mascorro pulled his pistol and began firing, shooting seven times.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Brandi Laramore hid in the home’s bathroom. According to the DCI report, she took the family dog into the bathroom with her. But in a frame from the body camera footage, the dog runs across the trailer floor as Mascorro, now standing, aims his gun toward Laramore.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="430" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=780%2C430&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-113673" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=1024%2C564&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=300%2C165&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=768%2C423&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=1200%2C661&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=780%2C430&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM.png?resize=400%2C220&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM.png?w=1400&amp;ssl=1 1400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Screenshot-2025-05-02-at-9.29.47%E2%80%AFAM-1024x564.png?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A screenshot from Sgt. Michael Mascorro’s body-worn camera footage shows him pointing his gun toward a doorway behind which Buck Laramore stood in April 2023. Mascorro broke into the home without a warrant and the two men shot each other. Laramore died. (Thermopolis Police Department footage)</figcaption></figure>



<p>It’s unclear if Mascorro hit Laramore during his first fusillade. Laramore appears to have retreated into another room of the trailer. According to the lawsuit, Laramore then stepped into Mascorro’s line of sight, now unarmed, and the officer fired three times. According to Mascorro’s interview with DCI agents, the officer believed Laramore was tactically peering around the corner and was still trying to shoot and kill him.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mascorro hit Laramore with his first shot, he believed, and possibly his second.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This time it was Laramore who fell to the ground and yelled, “stop, stop,” according to the lawsuit.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mascorro, now severely weakened by his injuries, collapsed to the floor. He was able to stagger out of the home before collapsing again in the yard, where arriving officers found him.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Inside the trailer, Laramore died in his wife’s arms, she told DCI agents.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Medics airlifted Mascorro to a hospital in Casper, where the officer came in and out of consciousness. When Mascorro returned to Thermopolis, he did so as a hero, welcomed with a parade, according to the Cowboy State Daily. However, after Erramouspe cleared Mascorro of any homicide charges but found he should not have entered Laramore’s home, the Peace Officer Standards and Training Commission again investigated the officer and considered decertifying him.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Decertifying an officer is the review board’s strongest and rarely used sanction — it would have prevented Mascorro from working in law enforcement anywhere in Wyoming.&nbsp;</p>



<p>POST, led at the time by former Casper police chief Chris Walsh, chose not to take that step. After a review of Erramouspe’s findings, the DCI report, state law and department policy, town officials in June 2024 decided Mascorro would return to duty.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“The Town believes Sgt. Mascaro did not violate policy or the law,” Thermopolis Mayor Adam Estenson said in a statement announcing the officer’s return.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I look forward to continued conversation on what policing looks like for Thermopolis into the future,” he continued.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Though the shootout was the town’s first police killing, according to an October 2023 statement from Estenson, a second would soon follow. In September 2024, a different Thermopolis police officer conducting a wellness check would run into a mentally ill man, Jared Gottula, who was swinging a bat wildly in his yard. Gottula advanced on the officer’s patrol vehicle and the officer struck him with it. During the tense encounter that followed, the officer and a Hot Springs County sheriff’s deputy fired more than 20 rounds, killing Gottula.</p>



<p>A review found the officers began shooting after Gottula advanced on the deputy with the bat raised. Both officers were cleared of any wrongdoing, and to date, no lawsuit has been filed.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/wrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home/">Wrongful death suit challenges Thermopolis cop for illegally entering home</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/wrongful-death-suit-challenges-thermopolis-cop-for-illegally-entering-home/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">113692</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Judge: Rock Springs school didn’t violate parental rights in transgender pronoun case</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/judge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/judge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joshua Wolfson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 19:49:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=113591</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="225" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=2000%2C1500&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="768" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=2000%2C1500&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>School district officials, educators did not keep information from high schooler’s parents or violate mother’s religious rights, federal judge concludes.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/judge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case/">Judge: Rock Springs school didn’t violate parental rights in transgender pronoun case</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="225" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=2000%2C1500&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="768" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=2000%2C1500&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6235-scaled.jpeg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fjudge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case%2F&amp;linkname=Judge%3A%20Rock%20Springs%20school%20didn%E2%80%99t%20violate%20parental%20rights%20in%20transgender%20pronoun%20case" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fjudge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case%2F&amp;linkname=Judge%3A%20Rock%20Springs%20school%20didn%E2%80%99t%20violate%20parental%20rights%20in%20transgender%20pronoun%20case" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fjudge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case%2F&amp;linkname=Judge%3A%20Rock%20Springs%20school%20didn%E2%80%99t%20violate%20parental%20rights%20in%20transgender%20pronoun%20case" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fjudge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case%2F&amp;linkname=Judge%3A%20Rock%20Springs%20school%20didn%E2%80%99t%20violate%20parental%20rights%20in%20transgender%20pronoun%20case" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fjudge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case%2F&amp;linkname=Judge%3A%20Rock%20Springs%20school%20didn%E2%80%99t%20violate%20parental%20rights%20in%20transgender%20pronoun%20case" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fjudge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case%2F&#038;title=Judge%3A%20Rock%20Springs%20school%20didn%E2%80%99t%20violate%20parental%20rights%20in%20transgender%20pronoun%20case" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/judge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case/" data-a2a-title="Judge: Rock Springs school didn’t violate parental rights in transgender pronoun case"></a></p>
<p>Sweetwater County educators did not keep information from the parents of a Rock Springs high school student who asked to be called by a preferred name and pronouns, a federal judge ruled Monday.</p>



<p>U.S. District Judge Scott Skavdahl reached that conclusion en route to dismissing a lawsuit brought by the child’s parents, who had alleged the district violated their rights by deliberately concealing information about their child’s name and pronoun choices. The student’s mother, a public school teacher in Sweetwater County, further alleged that her First Amendment religious rights were violated by district policies that direct staff about how to handle students’ preferred names and pronouns.</p>



<p>Skavdahl rebuffed both allegations, agreeing with Sweetwater County School District 1 lawyers that the case should be decided in the educators’ favor before it reached a jury.</p>



<p>“The undisputed facts establish that Defendants did not withhold or knowingly misrepresent any information regarding the Student from or to Plaintiff, and thus did not interfere with this right,” Skavdahl wrote. “Neither did Defendants’ conduct burden Plaintiff’s First Amendment right to freely exercise her religious beliefs as a parent or unconstitutionally interfere with her right to freely exercise her religious beliefs as a teacher.”</p>



<p>The student’s parents, Ashley and Sean Willey, sued Sweetwater County School District 1 leaders and educators in April 2023. They asked the court to bar the district from using any names or pronouns other than the ones their teenager was given at birth without prior written consent.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Ashley Willey also asked the court to block the district from forcing her, as a teacher, to use her students’ preferred pronouns or names. Willey did not use students’ preferred pronouns and names as a teacher, and she testified she was never disciplined or retaliated against for her decision, according to Skavdahl’s ruling.</p>



<p>The Willey family filed the lawsuit amid rising concerns, often expressed by conservative-leaning parents, that schools were influencing student decisions about gender identity. That spurred efforts to <a href="https://wyofile.com/book-challenges-content-controversies-roil-fremont-county-libraries/">ban or limit access to certain LGBTQ+ books</a> at school and public libraries in Wyoming. State lawmakers also brought measures designed to <a href="https://wyoleg.gov/Legislation/2025/HB0200">prevent school districts</a> and <a href="https://wyoleg.gov/Legislation/2025/SF0077">public employees</a> from being required to use preferred pronouns and names, while requiring schools to provide parents with more information about their children. A school district pronoun bill died in the state Senate while the state-employee focused legislation became law without Gov. Mark Gordon’s signature.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="585" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=780%2C585&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-98724" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest.jpeg?w=1500&amp;ssl=1 1500w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/libraryprotest-1024x768.jpeg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Three women protest in front of the Lander Library on April 17, 2024. The women, who were reciting prayers, did not give their names. (Anna Goforth/WyoFile) </figcaption></figure>



<p>Earlier this year, Wyoming’s schools superintendent, Megan Degenfelder, <a href="https://edu.wyoming.gov/wyoming-superintendent-of-public-instruction-megan-degenfelder-announces-2025-legislative-priorities/">also pushed for a requirement</a> that schools receive parental consent before using a child’s preferred name or pronouns.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Parental rights, district obligations</strong></h4>



<p>In the Willeys’ lawsuit, the parents alleged their child asked teachers and staff at Black Butte High School in Rock Springs to be called by a male name and pronouns starting in the 2021-22 school year. They accused the district of keeping that development from them by continuing to use the child’s gender assigned at birth in their presence, while using the teen’s preferred name and pronouns in school.&nbsp;</p>



<p>During depositions, three school staff members testified they used the student’s preferred name and pronouns during the 2021-22 school year. Another teacher did so in an email exchange during the 2022-23 school year.</p>



<p>The Willeys asserted that the district should have proactively informed them about their child’s change in name and pronouns because parents have a right to make decisions about their children’s well-being, including their physical and mental health.&nbsp;</p>



<p>But Skavdahl noted that such a stance would be impractical, as there are a “laundry list of circumstances that could affect a child’s ‘well-being’ even in the slightest that would require constant, detailed information sharing from the school, with constitutional consequences.”</p>



<p>The judge agreed that parents have a right to know about their child’s gender identity choices if parents seek that information from schools. But he drew a distinction between a district knowingly keeping that information from a parent and a district that provides such information only when asked.</p>



<p>“The Court does not think the information can properly be deemed ‘withheld’ to infringe on parental rights unless a parent inquired into or sought the information and it was intentionally concealed or they were lied to,” Skavdahl wrote. “Otherwise, an infinite amount of information would be deemed ‘withheld’ by schools on a daily basis in violation of parental rights.”</p>



<p>“The District and its staff members merely respected the Student’s voluntary choice to be referred to by preferred name and pronouns,” the judge wrote later in the opinion. “Neither the District nor its staff members required the Student go by preferred name or pronouns nor did they ‘discourage students from discussing their gender identities with their parents.’”</p>



<p>Moreover, the school district shared information with the parents about their child’s preferred name and pronouns when that information was sought, the judge noted.</p>



<p>Skavdahl also rejected the Willeys’ arguments that educators facilitated the student’s gender transition socially, and thus, invalidated the parents’ right to make medical decisions for their teen.</p>



<p>“Plaintiff offers no evidence that the school provided any type of ‘medical transition’ or even ‘facilitated’ the Student’s ‘social transitioning,’” Skavdahl wrote. “Defendants were not involved in changing the Student’s clothing or hairstyle. Plaintiff did not set forth any facts that staff members even encouraged or suggested the Student engage in such behaviors, but simply that staff members passively respected the Student’s request to be referred to by preferred name and pronouns.”</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Freedom of religion</strong></h4>



<p>Skavdahl also denied Ashley Willey’s claims that the district violated her freedom of religion, both as a parent and as a teacher. She had argued the district’s failure to inform her about her child’s gender identity changes interfered with her religious beliefs because it kept her from information she needed to counsel her child.</p>



<p>But that reasoning would create an obligation on the part of the district to foster the exercise of Willey’s religious beliefs, the judge wrote.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-pullquote"><blockquote><p>To conclude that the District’s failure to act in accordance with Plaintiff’s religious beliefs is a constitutional violation would turn the First Amendment on its head.”</p><cite>Judge scott skavdahl</cite></blockquote></figure>



<p>“Plaintiff’s allegations, more plainly, are that the District staff members’ use, at the Student’s request, of preferred name and pronouns were counter to Plaintiff’s own religious beliefs,” he wrote. “However, a person’s constitutional right to freely exercise their own religious beliefs does not require that the state also exercise those same religious beliefs … To conclude that the District’s failure to act in accordance with Plaintiff’s religious beliefs is a constitutional violation would turn the First Amendment on its head.”</p>



<p>As to Willey’s assertions that being required to follow the district’s policies concerning preferred pronouns and names violated her religious rights, Skavdahl was unswayed. Those policies were “neutral laws of general applicability,” they don’t raise concerns about the free exercise of religion and must only be “rationally related to a legitimate government interest” to be considered constitutional. That interest, Skavdahl wrote, involved promoting an educational environment that’s both respectful and without discrimination.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/judge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case/">Judge: Rock Springs school didn’t violate parental rights in transgender pronoun case</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/judge-rock-springs-school-didnt-violate-parental-rights-in-transgender-pronoun-case/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>17</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">113591</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Woman killed when Casper police responded to burglary report lived at the home, court documents show</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/woman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/woman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andrew Graham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 20:32:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law enforcement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[casper police department]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jody cobia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[officer involved shooting]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=113554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="214" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?fit=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=1024%2C731&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=768%2C548&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=780%2C557&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=400%2C286&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?fit=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="731" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?fit=1024%2C731&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=1024%2C731&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=768%2C548&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=780%2C557&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=400%2C286&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?fit=1024%2C731&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>One person died at a Casper home Monday after police received a report of an armed burglar. Court files reviewed by WyoFile show she was listed as a legal resident of the house.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/woman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show/">Woman killed when Casper police responded to burglary report lived at the home, court documents show</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="214" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?fit=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=1024%2C731&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=768%2C548&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=780%2C557&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=400%2C286&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?fit=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="731" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?fit=1024%2C731&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=300%2C214&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=1024%2C731&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=768%2C548&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=780%2C557&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?resize=400%2C286&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6222.jpg?fit=1024%2C731&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwoman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show%2F&amp;linkname=Woman%20killed%20when%20Casper%20police%20responded%20to%20burglary%20report%20lived%20at%20the%20home%2C%20court%20documents%20show" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwoman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show%2F&amp;linkname=Woman%20killed%20when%20Casper%20police%20responded%20to%20burglary%20report%20lived%20at%20the%20home%2C%20court%20documents%20show" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwoman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show%2F&amp;linkname=Woman%20killed%20when%20Casper%20police%20responded%20to%20burglary%20report%20lived%20at%20the%20home%2C%20court%20documents%20show" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwoman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show%2F&amp;linkname=Woman%20killed%20when%20Casper%20police%20responded%20to%20burglary%20report%20lived%20at%20the%20home%2C%20court%20documents%20show" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwoman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show%2F&amp;linkname=Woman%20killed%20when%20Casper%20police%20responded%20to%20burglary%20report%20lived%20at%20the%20home%2C%20court%20documents%20show" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwoman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show%2F&#038;title=Woman%20killed%20when%20Casper%20police%20responded%20to%20burglary%20report%20lived%20at%20the%20home%2C%20court%20documents%20show" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/woman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show/" data-a2a-title="Woman killed when Casper police responded to burglary report lived at the home, court documents show"></a></p>
<p>A woman killed Monday morning during an encounter with police responding to a burglary report at a Casper residence is listed in court documents as living in the home.</p>



<p>Police have declined to say if the person killed was a criminal suspect or the resident of the house, but court records examined by WyoFile indicate the woman, 37-year-old Jody Cobia, legally resided at the home.</p>



<p>Casper police officers responded to the 1600 block of South McKinley Street, a residential neighborhood in the central part of the city, around 12:36 a.m. Monday. They were responding to a report of an armed burglar in the residence, according to a police statement.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The officers “made contact with a subject armed with a firearm,” shots were fired and the woman was then taken to the hospital, where doctors declared her dead, the statement said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The statement is not explicit about whether officers shot Cobia. “During the encounter, shots were fired,” it reads.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224.jpg?resize=768%2C1024&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-113548" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=1152%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 1152w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C2048&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=900%2C1200&amp;ssl=1 900w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=600%2C800&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=450%2C600&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C400&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=150%2C200&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C1600&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C2667&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=780%2C1040&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C533&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-scaled.jpg?w=1920&amp;ssl=1 1920w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/IMG_6224-768x1024.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The open door of a home on South McKinley Street in Casper. Jody Cobia, the 37-year-old who lived at the home, was shot and killed as police responded to a burglar just after midnight on April 28. (Joshua Wolfson/WyoFile)</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>A department official declined to provide WyoFile with additional information Monday morning, including whether the person who was shot lived at the home, citing the early stages of the investigation.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Early Monday afternoon, the Natrona County Coroners’ Office identified the dead woman as Cobia. Court records reviewed by WyoFile indicate she had sole legal possession of the home as part of a protection order granted in August, though tax records put the home in her husband’s name.</p>



<p>According to the filings, Cobia was the mother of three children and was in the early stages of a divorce from her husband. Court records indicate Cobia petitioned a judge for, and received, a protection order from her husband in August.&nbsp;</p>



<p>That protection order, reviewed by WyoFile, granted Cobia sole possession of the house, 1623 S. McKinley Street, until August of this year. Multiple court documents list the McKinley Street address as her residence.</p>



<p>Mid-morning Monday, a WyoFile journalist observed that the door of 1623 S. McKinley street remained slightly open, though there was no other evidence of an active crime scene investigation nearly 12 hours after the shooting.&nbsp;</p>



<p>On Monday, Casper Police Capt. Jeremy Tremel declined to say whether the person shot was the home resident or a burglary suspect, or whether there was a burglary suspect on the scene. “All I can tell you right now is we responded to a report of a suspected burglary,” he said.</p>



<p>He did not immediately respond to a second request for comment after the coroner published its identification.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Cobia’s husband, Aren Cobia, indicated he was a resident of the home in a divorce petition filed earlier this month. But the court record also indicates Jody Cobia was served with the divorce petition, in person, at the South McKinley Street address on April 15.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Reached briefly by WyoFile, Aren Cobia asked for time to grieve Jody Cobia’s death and declined to otherwise comment. Aren Cobia told a reporter from another news outlet, Cowboy State Daily, that there was no burglar in the home and police had killed his wife. </p>



<p>The Wyoming Division of Criminal Investigation will investigate the shooting. After police shootings, it’s typical for DCI to conduct an investigation and then provide the findings of that review to an elected county attorney. The prosecutor then decides whether or not to charge officers with any crimes. Prosecutors, in some cases, refer that decision to an outside county attorney to bring an additional level of independence to the investigation.</p>



<p>The officers involved in the shooting are now on administrative leave, according to the department’s news release.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Officials did not describe the person shot as a suspect in that news release, only as a “subject armed with a firearm.” Because of the ambiguity of the official statement, commenters on social media, as well as two Wyoming news outlets, described the deceased as a criminal suspect.</p>



<p>“Suspected burglar dead in Casper Police shooting,” was the headline on an initial Cowboy State Daily story that was online throughout the morning Monday. By the early afternoon, the news site had updated that headline to “One dead in officer-involved shooting during Casper burglary response,” and the site had issued a correction. </p>



<p>“Suspect dead after Casper police respond to armed burglary,” Casper-news site Oil City News reported.&nbsp;</p>



<p>On Facebook, a large number of commenters commended the officers who responded to the home and in several instances suggested a burglary suspect deserved to be killed. “Finally a story with a happy ending,” one commenter wrote. “Clearly he valued their stuff more than his life and got what he deserved,” wrote another.&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>WyoFile editor Joshua Wolfson contributed reporting from Casper.</em></p>



<p></p>



<p><em>&nbsp;</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/woman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show/">Woman killed when Casper police responded to burglary report lived at the home, court documents show</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/woman-killed-when-casper-police-responded-to-burglary-report-lived-at-the-home-court-documents-show/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>11</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">113554</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Animated elderly woman behind police incident at Hageman town hall in Wheatland, report shows</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/animated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/animated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andrew Graham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 16:58:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law enforcement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[animated elderly woman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harriet Hageman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[protests]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[town hall]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wheatland police department]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=113490</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="200" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1365&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C800&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1045&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1333&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C267&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="683" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1365&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C800&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1045&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1333&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C267&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>A woman approached Hageman after a Wheatland town hall and waved her hands in the congresswoman’s face, causing an officer to intervene. The woman apologized.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/animated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows/">Animated elderly woman behind police incident at Hageman town hall in Wheatland, report shows</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="200" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1365&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C800&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1045&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1333&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C267&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="683" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1365&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C800&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1045&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1333&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C267&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_7864-scaled.jpg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fanimated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows%2F&amp;linkname=Animated%20elderly%20woman%20behind%20police%20incident%20at%20Hageman%20town%20hall%20in%20Wheatland%2C%20report%20shows" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fanimated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows%2F&amp;linkname=Animated%20elderly%20woman%20behind%20police%20incident%20at%20Hageman%20town%20hall%20in%20Wheatland%2C%20report%20shows" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fanimated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows%2F&amp;linkname=Animated%20elderly%20woman%20behind%20police%20incident%20at%20Hageman%20town%20hall%20in%20Wheatland%2C%20report%20shows" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fanimated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows%2F&amp;linkname=Animated%20elderly%20woman%20behind%20police%20incident%20at%20Hageman%20town%20hall%20in%20Wheatland%2C%20report%20shows" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fanimated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows%2F&amp;linkname=Animated%20elderly%20woman%20behind%20police%20incident%20at%20Hageman%20town%20hall%20in%20Wheatland%2C%20report%20shows" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fanimated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows%2F&#038;title=Animated%20elderly%20woman%20behind%20police%20incident%20at%20Hageman%20town%20hall%20in%20Wheatland%2C%20report%20shows" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/animated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows/" data-a2a-title="Animated elderly woman behind police incident at Hageman town hall in Wheatland, report shows"></a></p>
<p>Following a March town hall in Wheatland, an elderly woman approached Rep. Harriet Hageman and spoke in an “aggressive manner” with her hands close to the representative’s face, a Wheatland Police Department report released to WyoFile this week shows.&nbsp;</p>



<p>One of Hageman’s staff members moved between the elderly woman and the lawmaker, and a Wheatland police officer took hold of the elderly woman’s wrists. The woman apologized and walked away, according to the report. No charges were filed and the officer does not appear to have taken down the woman’s name.&nbsp;</p>



<p>There were no other incidents that required law enforcement either during or after the event, <a href="https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/W25-0808-Report-Request-WyoFile-1.pdf">according to Wheatland Police Sgt. Dalton Minsaas&#8217; report</a>. </p>



<p>Hageman <a href="https://wyofile.com/hageman-cancels-in-person-town-halls-opts-for-virtual-events-citing-safety-concerns/">cited the Wheatland incident</a> as one of the safety threats that spurred her to move her town halls online for a time. Hageman this week restarted in-person town halls in Buffalo and Dayton, but required people to register for them ahead of time.</p>



<p>The Wheatland police report aligns with Hageman’s account of the incident, but provides more detail. &nbsp;</p>



<p>“An attendee followed Hageman leaving the venue and initiated a physical confrontation with staff, into which local police were forced to intervene,” Hageman’s staff wrote in their March statement about moving town halls online.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The March 20 Wheatland town hall followed a raucous event in Laramie the night before, where <a href="https://wyofile.com/crowd-jeers-hageman-at-tense-laramie-town-hall-she-calls-them-hysterical/">Hageman was booed and heckled by people</a> upset by the actions of President Donald Trump and his billionaire ally Elon Musk. Still, law enforcement at the Laramie event told WyoFile there were no incidents and officers did not remove anyone.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="520" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-38.jpg?resize=780%2C520&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-112214" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-38.jpg?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-38.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-38.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-38.jpg?resize=400%2C267&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-38.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-38-1024x683.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">People wait to address U.S. Rep. Harriet Hageman on March 19, 2025, at her town hall event in Laramie. (Megan Johnson/WyoFile)</figcaption></figure>



<p>In Wheatland, security was significant and led by the Platte County Sheriff’s Office. Four Wheatland PD officers joined deputies guarding the event, with different assignments, according to a second police report released to WyoFile, this one written by Sgt. Russell Swingle.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Hageman also cited the strain placed on law enforcement resources as a reason for moving her events online. In Buffalo on Thursday night, she met a mixed reception that included both support and jeering, the Cowboy State Daily reported.&nbsp;</p>



<p>There were no incidents that required an intervention from law enforcement, Buffalo Police Department Captain Garth Nicholas told WyoFile on Friday.&nbsp;</p>



<p>WyoFile requested the Wheatland reports under the Wyoming Public Records Act on March 27. They were released Thursday, although it’s not clear when the reports were written. Traci Swingle, the department’s administrative assistant, told WyoFile she was unable to provide that information.&nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Constituent anger</strong></h4>



<p>Republican lawmakers nationwide have faced anger and indignation from their constituents when they’ve returned from Washington, D.C. to their home states, as the Musk-led DOGE initiative continues to <a href="https://wyofile.com/valentines-day-massacre-uncounted-throng-of-wyomingites-fired-by-trump-administration/">sharply reduce</a> and <a href="https://wyofile.com/trump-and-musks-doge-functionally-destroying-historic-yellowstone-grizzly-science-team/">restructure government programs</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Hageman cast the people who heckled her in Laramie and elsewhere as organized protesters, and some conservatives falsely suggested they had come into the state from elsewhere to flood the events — or were even paid protesters.</p>



<p>The police reports show Hageman faced upset constituents in Wheatland too.</p>



<p>“During the town hall, I could hear ‘boos’ from the crowd,” wrote Swingle, who was posted in the lobby of Wheatland High School, where the town hall was held.</p>



<p>Minsaas was standing by the high school auditorium’s entrance as people were exiting. Hageman came up a set of stairs toward the doors where Minsaas was posted, and the officer watched “an elderly female” who was “moving in a quick manner to get close to Hageman.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>One of Hageman’s staffers, who is not named in the report, stepped between the two women, Minsaas wrote. Hageman’s staff did not respond to a WyoFile request for additional details about the incident.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“The elderly female was communicating to Hageman in what appeared to be an aggressive manner,” Minsaas wrote. “I also observed the elderly female’s hands were up and close to Hageman’s face.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>The officer “gained control” of the constituent’s wrists, he wrote, and “explained to her that she could communicate with Hageman, but she needed to keep her hands to her side.” The woman apologized and walked away.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Hageman’s staff and law enforcement walked with the congresswoman out of the building.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“There is nothing further to report on this matter,” Minsaas concluded.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/animated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows/">Animated elderly woman behind police incident at Hageman town hall in Wheatland, report shows</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/animated-elderly-woman-behind-police-incident-at-hageman-town-hall-in-wheatland-report-shows/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>38</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">113490</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wyoming Supreme Court weighs $3M dispute over fuel industry tax break</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/wyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/wyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dustin Bleizeffer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 20:24:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Natural Resources]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=113435</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="206" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?fit=300%2C206&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=300%2C206&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=1024%2C701&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=768%2C526&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=400%2C274&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?fit=300%2C206&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="701" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?fit=1024%2C701&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=300%2C206&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=1024%2C701&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=768%2C526&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=400%2C274&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?fit=1024%2C701&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>Local governments could face clawbacks if Merit Energy wins tax exemption intended for "transportation" companies.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/wyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break/">Wyoming Supreme Court weighs $3M dispute over fuel industry tax break</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="206" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?fit=300%2C206&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=300%2C206&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=1024%2C701&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=768%2C526&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=400%2C274&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?fit=300%2C206&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="701" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?fit=1024%2C701&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=300%2C206&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=1024%2C701&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=768%2C526&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?resize=400%2C274&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Oil-site-aerial-view-PRB-2024-DBleizeffer.jpg?fit=1024%2C701&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break%2F&amp;linkname=Wyoming%20Supreme%20Court%20weighs%20%243M%20dispute%20over%20fuel%20industry%20tax%20break" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break%2F&amp;linkname=Wyoming%20Supreme%20Court%20weighs%20%243M%20dispute%20over%20fuel%20industry%20tax%20break" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break%2F&amp;linkname=Wyoming%20Supreme%20Court%20weighs%20%243M%20dispute%20over%20fuel%20industry%20tax%20break" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break%2F&amp;linkname=Wyoming%20Supreme%20Court%20weighs%20%243M%20dispute%20over%20fuel%20industry%20tax%20break" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break%2F&amp;linkname=Wyoming%20Supreme%20Court%20weighs%20%243M%20dispute%20over%20fuel%20industry%20tax%20break" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fwyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break%2F&#038;title=Wyoming%20Supreme%20Court%20weighs%20%243M%20dispute%20over%20fuel%20industry%20tax%20break" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/wyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break/" data-a2a-title="Wyoming Supreme Court weighs $3M dispute over fuel industry tax break"></a></p>
<p>Millions of dollars are at stake for oil and gas producing counties in a case before the Wyoming Supreme Court to decide whether a sales tax exemption applies to companies that used electricity to move their products from wellheads to a point of sale.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Department of Revenue is asking the Wyoming Supreme Court to overturn a 2024 State Board of Equalization ruling in favor of Merit Energy Company, which says it is entitled to a $3 million sales tax refund — in addition to earlier refunds — for the electrical power it purchased from 2020 through 2023 to transport oil and gas via pipeline.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Entangled in the lawsuit is electrical provider PacifiCorp, which seeks to collect the refund on Merit&#8217;s behalf. If the court sides with PacifiCorp and Merit, it could financially burden local governments that have received sales tax revenues based on the Department of Revenue&#8217;s interpretation of the sales tax exemption.</p>



<p>Park County officials, for example, said last year they were stunned to learn that local governments there might have to repay about $743,000, <a href="https://www.powelltribune.com/stories/53-million-refunded-to-producer,116729">the Powell Tribune reported</a>.</p>



<p>If Merit wins, other oil and gas companies will likely file for similar refunds, resulting in revenue &#8220;clawbacks&#8221; to the tune of &#8220;millions of dollars, but not tens of millions,&#8221; impacting most counties where there&#8217;s oil and gas production, according to a Department of Revenue official.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="585" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Oil-rig-Wyoming.jpg?resize=780%2C585&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-44737" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Oil-rig-Wyoming.jpg?w=1000&amp;ssl=1 1000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Oil-rig-Wyoming.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Oil-rig-Wyoming.jpg?resize=728%2C546&amp;ssl=1 728w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Oil-rig-Wyoming.jpg?resize=745%2C559&amp;ssl=1 745w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Oil-rig-Wyoming.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Oil-rig-Wyoming.jpg?w=400&amp;ssl=1 400w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">This rig was drilling for oil north of Casper in 2014. (Dustin Bleizeffer/WyoFile)</figcaption></figure>



<p>No matter which way the court rules, Merit&#8217;s view of the sales tax exemption will be enshrined in state statute, beginning July 1. <a href="https://www.wyoleg.gov/Legislation/2025/HB0311">House Bill 311, &#8220;Exemption for transported fuel and power sales-amendments</a>,&#8221; passed earlier this year, clarifies that such utility expenses qualify.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>&#8216;Transportation&#8217; or &#8216;gathering&#8217;?</strong></h4>



<p>The soon-to-be-outdated state <a href="https://law.justia.com/codes/wyoming/title-39/chapter-15/article-1/section-39-15-105/">sales tax exemption</a> in question before the court applies to &#8220;Sales of power or fuel to a person transporting tangible personal property by railroad or by pipeline when the power or fuel is consumed directly in generating motive power for actual transportation purposes.&#8221;</p>



<p>The case hinges on whether or not Merit — and presumably other oil and gas producers in the state — qualify as a &#8220;transportation&#8221; company when it comes to moving their products to purchase points in the pipeline network.</p>



<p>Merit, one of the top oil and gas producers in the state, says the Department of Revenue has waffled on the classification, arguing on some occasions that oil and gas producers are in the business of transporting goods while also arguing they are not primarily transportation companies.</p>





<p>&#8220;Merit is in the oil and gas transportation business,&#8221; Merit attorneys wrote in a <a href="https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Brief-of-Appellee-Merit-Energy-Company-LLC.pdf">brief</a> filed with the court on Monday. &#8220;It gets paid to transport other entities’ oil from wellheads to a point of sale. Merit is thus no different than an interstate trucking company or a railroad, except that instead of using trucks and roads or locomotives and rails, Merit uses submersible electric pumps and pipelines.&#8221;</p>



<p>The Department of Revenue, in a March <a href="https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Brief-Petitioner.pdf">brief</a>, noted that Board of Equalization Vice-Chairman Martin L. Hardsocg dissented in the board&#8217;s ruling. Rather than transporting, according to Hardsocg&#8217;s dissent, Merit is in the business of &#8220;gathering&#8221; petrol commodities, which is more closely tied to production.</p>



<p>&#8220;Because Merit&#8217;s primary function is to operate various units and produce and sell oil and gas, including moving oil through a gathering system, it does not meet the statutory requirements for the exemption because it is not in the business of transporting oil through a pipeline,&#8221; according to the department&#8217;s brief.</p>



<p>No hearing dates have been set in the case initiated in January.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/wyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break/">Wyoming Supreme Court weighs $3M dispute over fuel industry tax break</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/wyoming-supreme-court-weighs-3m-dispute-over-fuel-industry-tax-break/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">113435</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Barrasso, Lummis, Hageman deride concerned Wyoming jurists as ‘biased,’ ‘liberal’</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/barrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/barrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andrew Graham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 10:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[boasberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[constitutional crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cynthia Lummis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harriet Hageman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[harvie wilkinson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Barrasso]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rule of law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wyoming jurists]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=113386</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="225" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="768" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>"Many of us know at least one of the delegates. And we know they know better," one attorney said, after the delegation labeled a broad group of jurists "biased."</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/barrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal/">Barrasso, Lummis, Hageman deride concerned Wyoming jurists as ‘biased,’ ‘liberal’</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="225" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="768" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1 780w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/delegationlawcollage.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fbarrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal%2F&amp;linkname=Barrasso%2C%20Lummis%2C%20Hageman%20deride%20concerned%20Wyoming%20jurists%20as%20%E2%80%98biased%2C%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%98liberal%E2%80%99" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fbarrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal%2F&amp;linkname=Barrasso%2C%20Lummis%2C%20Hageman%20deride%20concerned%20Wyoming%20jurists%20as%20%E2%80%98biased%2C%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%98liberal%E2%80%99" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fbarrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal%2F&amp;linkname=Barrasso%2C%20Lummis%2C%20Hageman%20deride%20concerned%20Wyoming%20jurists%20as%20%E2%80%98biased%2C%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%98liberal%E2%80%99" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fbarrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal%2F&amp;linkname=Barrasso%2C%20Lummis%2C%20Hageman%20deride%20concerned%20Wyoming%20jurists%20as%20%E2%80%98biased%2C%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%98liberal%E2%80%99" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fbarrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal%2F&amp;linkname=Barrasso%2C%20Lummis%2C%20Hageman%20deride%20concerned%20Wyoming%20jurists%20as%20%E2%80%98biased%2C%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%98liberal%E2%80%99" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fbarrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal%2F&#038;title=Barrasso%2C%20Lummis%2C%20Hageman%20deride%20concerned%20Wyoming%20jurists%20as%20%E2%80%98biased%2C%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%98liberal%E2%80%99" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/barrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal/" data-a2a-title="Barrasso, Lummis, Hageman deride concerned Wyoming jurists as ‘biased,’ ‘liberal’"></a></p>
<p>Amid mounting concerns about White House disregard of court orders, Wyoming’s congressional delegates made clear last week that they continue to support President Donald Trump’s defiance of the federal judiciary.</p>



<p>And they are willing to insult their own constituents in defense of that position.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Rep. Harriet Hageman and Sens. Cynthia Lummis and John Barrasso publicly derided a distinguished swath of the Wyoming Bar while dismissing concerns those constituents raised in a <a href="https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/2025-03-26-Letter-to-Hageman-Lummis-Barrasso-With-Signatures.pdf">March 26 letter</a> warning that Trump and his allies’ threats could erode the country’s rule of law.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Wyoming’s federal delegation lashed out at the letter&#8217;s signees the same week federal judges warned that the Trump administration was striking at the core of the constitutional system that protects Americans from an unruly or oppressive government.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The more than 100 Wyoming jurists who put their name on the letter asking the delegation to protect the rule of law included three former state Supreme Court justices, an ex-governor, two former state attorneys general appointed by governors from both political parties, veteran attorneys and young Wyoming lawyers making their start in the profession.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Among the names were those of Republican and Democrat politicians and the former law partner of Rep. Harriet Hageman’s husband. Though their leanings covered the political spectrum, they shared one thing in common: Mounting concern that the rule of law is under extreme duress.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In response, Lummis, Hageman and Barrasso described the signatories as “biased, misguided” and “liberal,” in a press release issued last week.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The delegation’s response came in two phases — the first <a href="https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Delegation-Response-to-Judges-Letter-Final.pdf">was an April 11 letter</a> rebuffing the Wyoming jurists’ concerns. Overreaching judges, not President Donald Trump’s threats, have placed the federal judiciary in the crosshairs, the delegation wrote.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="520" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-26.jpg?resize=780%2C520&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-112212" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-26.jpg?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-26.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-26.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-26.jpg?resize=400%2C267&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-26.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-26-1024x683.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">U.S. Rep. Harriet Hageman, R-Wyo., addresses an often-hostile crowd on March 19, 2025, in Laramie. (Megan Johnson/WyoFile)</figcaption></figure>



<p>That letter ended with an olive branch. “We look forward to working with each of you to secure a prosperous future for Wyoming and to ensure a return to the non-partisan rule of law,” the delegates wrote.&nbsp;</p>



<p>On April 15, however, after WyoFile <a href="https://wyofile.com/called-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem/">reporting</a> made their letter public, the delegation dropped any niceties and issued a press release headlined: “Wyoming Delegation Responds to Biased, Misguided WY Judges and Lawyers.”</p>



<p>The delegate’s letter itself was “extremely dispiriting,” Jackson attorney Bill Schwartz, one of the letter’s signees, told WyoFile on April 17. But he had not yet seen the press release.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Well, that’s just preposterous,” he said, when a reporter described it to him. “These are very accomplished lawyers, from every part of the state, that went to the same law school as [Lummis and Hageman] did… Many of us know at least one of the delegates. And we know they know better.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>The delegation’s answer has dismayed the letter signers, who saw in it deeply worrying signs for the country’s democratic rule.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“We are, in my judgment, in very dangerous times,” Jackson attorney Bob Schuster wrote in an email to his fellow signees. “My concerns are only heightened by the cynical and unprincipled response from our Congressional delegation,” he added in the email obtained by WyoFile.</p>



<p>The three politicians, for their part, say they’re responding to “liberal former judges and lawyers attempting to publicly pressure the delegation into falsely condemning President Trump and allowing judges to continue blocking the agenda more than 70% of Wyoming residents support,” according to the press release.</p>



<p>In today’s Wyoming politics, “if you have an independent thought sometimes that makes you a liberal,” Gillette attorney Tom Lubnau said. As a Republican politician, Lubnau served in the Wyoming House from 2004 to 2014, rising to become Speaker of the House in his final term.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I’m going to take every opportunity I have to defend our court system and our constitutional system,” Lubnau told WyoFile. “Do I think the system is perfect? No. Do I think it’s the best system man has devised? Yes.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Lummis, Hageman and Barrasso did not respond to interview requests from WyoFile.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="776" height="560" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Donald_Trump_and_John_Barrasso.jpg?resize=776%2C560&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-111152" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Donald_Trump_and_John_Barrasso.jpg?w=776&amp;ssl=1 776w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Donald_Trump_and_John_Barrasso.jpg?resize=300%2C216&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Donald_Trump_and_John_Barrasso.jpg?resize=768%2C554&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Donald_Trump_and_John_Barrasso.jpg?resize=400%2C289&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Donald_Trump_and_John_Barrasso.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 776px) 100vw, 776px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">President Donald J. Trump, seated next to U.S. Sen. John Barrasso, R-WY, right, meets with members of Congress during his first presidential administration. (White House photo)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Lawyers and former judges who signed the letter say that even in the more restrained portion of the delegate’s response, the politicians misstated fundamental tenets of American law. Though disheartening, the delegation’s response has galvanized the letter&#8217;s signees to continue speaking up, and has led other Wyoming jurists to reach out and offer support, Schwartz said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The delegation issued its response during a week of ongoing clashes between the president and federal judges over the rights of migrants detained by the Trump administration and shipped to a prison in El Salvador.&nbsp;</p>



<p>On Wednesday, a federal judge in Washington, D.C. issued an order suggesting he could soon begin proceedings to hold the Trump administration in contempt of court. Trump had called for that judge, James Boasberg, to be impeached after Boasberg issued an injunction temporarily halting the president’s use of the Alien Enemies Act to detain people.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Trump invoked the act to justify his administration’s imprisonment of Venezuelans and other Latin Americans in El Salvador, without court hearings. The act was last used during World War II, when it led to the infamous internment of Japanese-Americans, including at Heart Mountain in Wyoming.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Heart Mountain Wyoming Foundation has also called on the delegation to check Trump’s use of the Alien Enemies Act. “The misuse of the Alien Enemies Act at that time makes us particularly sensitive to any future abuse of the law,” <a href="https://www.heartmountain.org/heart-mountain-seeks-wyoming-delegations-help-to-save-imls-limit-alien-enemies-act/">the foundation wrote in an April 1 statement</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The delegates did not respond to that message, though it was delivered to each of them, officials from Heart Mountain Wyoming Foundation told WyoFile Monday. </p>



<p>Concern over Trump’s suggestion that Boasberg should be impeached was central to the Wyoming jurists’ letter to the delegation. The signees called on Hageman, Barrasso and Lummis to speak against the idea that a judge could be personally targeted for a ruling the president didn’t like. Trump’s threat also drew a rare rebuke from U.S. Supreme Court Justice John Roberts.</p>





<p>The George W. Bush appointed chief justice said Trump was challenging two centuries of precedent, and that “impeachment is not an appropriate response to disagreement concerning a judicial decision.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>What’s at stake is far broader than the rights of those now imprisoned in El Salvador under Trump’s invocation of wartime powers, according to the signees of the letter to Wyoming’s delegation.</p>



<p>Schwartz, the Jackson attorney, and others pointed to a Thursday ruling and admonition penned by conservative, Ronald Reagan appointed judge Harvie Wilkinson, as an example of their concerns. </p>



<p>“The government is asserting a right to stash away residents of this country in foreign prisons without the semblance of due process that is the foundation of our constitutional order,” Wilkinson wrote. “This should be shocking not only to judges, but to the intuitive sense of liberty that Americans far removed from courthouses still hold dear.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>“If today the Executive claims the right to deport without due process and in disregard of court orders, what assurance will there be tomorrow that it will not deport American citizens and then disclaim responsibility to bring them home?” he continued.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Lummis on Thursday labeled Boasberg’s injunction pausing the deportations to, and imprisonments in, El Salvador as “one of the most shocking examples” of judicial overreach during the Trump administration.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Boasberg ordered planes full of dangerous illegal aliens and alleged Tren de Aragua gang members to turn around mid-flight and return to the United States,” Lummis wrote in an opinion column published by Cowboy State Daily.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="520" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?resize=780%2C520&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-111153" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?resize=1200%2C800&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?resize=1568%2C1046&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?resize=400%2C267&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2.jpg?w=1600&amp;ssl=1 1600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Cynthia_Lummis_at_Gillette_Wyoming_town_hall_2-1024x683.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Sen. Cynthia Lummis speaks at a town hall at the Gillette College Technical Education Center in Gillette, Wyoming in 2024. (Satterly, WikiCommons)</figcaption></figure>



<p>In the first three months of Trump’s presidency, judges have issued 15 nationwide injunctions on federal policies, Lummis wrote, one more than they did throughout the entirety of President Joe Biden’s term. “We must remember that judges are not policymakers – and they have not been elected by the American people to legislate. The people of Wyoming deserve a government where their elected representatives make the laws,” she wrote.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Her fellow Wyoming Bar members say she’s being disingenuous at best.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“You would think that any reasoned response to our letter might have paused to consider one of the first cases any of us read in our Constitutional Law course — Marbury v. Madison,” Schuster, the Jackson attorney, wrote in his email to colleagues. </p>



<p>That 1803 case established that the courts can find that laws passed by Congress and executive actions are unconstitutional. The delegation, Schuster continued, is arguing that “the Court really did not mean what they said and that its 222 years of lasting precedent … is vaporous.”&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/barrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal/">Barrasso, Lummis, Hageman deride concerned Wyoming jurists as ‘biased,’ ‘liberal’</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/barrasso-lummis-hageman-deride-concerned-wyoming-jurists-as-biased-liberal/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>38</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">113386</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Called on to defend the rule of law, Wyoming’s delegation says judges, not Trump, are the problem</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/called-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/called-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andrew Graham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 22:25:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cynthia Lummis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elon Musk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harriet Hageman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Barrasso]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[judiciary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marilyn Kite]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[michael davis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michael Golden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Sullivan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trump]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Downes]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=113086</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="198" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?fit=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=768%2C507&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1200%2C792&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=400%2C264&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?fit=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="676" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?fit=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=768%2C507&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1200%2C792&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=400%2C264&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?fit=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>Senators and rep. say Congress should curb judges’ authority. The comments came in response to jurists’ letter urging them to protect the rule of law.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/called-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem/">Called on to defend the rule of law, Wyoming’s delegation says judges, not Trump, are the problem</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="198" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?fit=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=768%2C507&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1200%2C792&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=400%2C264&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?fit=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="676" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?fit=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=768%2C507&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1200%2C792&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=400%2C264&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?fit=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcalled-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem%2F&amp;linkname=Called%20on%20to%20defend%20the%20rule%20of%20law%2C%20Wyoming%E2%80%99s%20delegation%20says%20judges%2C%20not%20Trump%2C%20are%20the%20problem" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcalled-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem%2F&amp;linkname=Called%20on%20to%20defend%20the%20rule%20of%20law%2C%20Wyoming%E2%80%99s%20delegation%20says%20judges%2C%20not%20Trump%2C%20are%20the%20problem" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcalled-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem%2F&amp;linkname=Called%20on%20to%20defend%20the%20rule%20of%20law%2C%20Wyoming%E2%80%99s%20delegation%20says%20judges%2C%20not%20Trump%2C%20are%20the%20problem" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcalled-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem%2F&amp;linkname=Called%20on%20to%20defend%20the%20rule%20of%20law%2C%20Wyoming%E2%80%99s%20delegation%20says%20judges%2C%20not%20Trump%2C%20are%20the%20problem" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcalled-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem%2F&amp;linkname=Called%20on%20to%20defend%20the%20rule%20of%20law%2C%20Wyoming%E2%80%99s%20delegation%20says%20judges%2C%20not%20Trump%2C%20are%20the%20problem" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcalled-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem%2F&#038;title=Called%20on%20to%20defend%20the%20rule%20of%20law%2C%20Wyoming%E2%80%99s%20delegation%20says%20judges%2C%20not%20Trump%2C%20are%20the%20problem" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/called-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem/" data-a2a-title="Called on to defend the rule of law, Wyoming’s delegation says judges, not Trump, are the problem"></a></p>
<p><br>The judiciary holds too much power and Congress should curb its authority, Wyoming’s federal delegation argued in response to Equality State lawyers and retired judges who called on them to defend “American Rule of Law” from attacks by President Donald Trump and his billionaire ally Elon Musk.</p>



<p><a href="https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/Delegation-Response-to-Judges-Letter-Final.pdf">In an April 11 letter</a>, Rep. Harriet Hageman and Sens. John Barrasso and Cynthia Lummis said the federal judiciary has drawn scrutiny on itself. “Unelected judges imposing their policy biases on our nation without democratic legitimacy are the root cause of today’s controversy,” they wrote.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The politicians largely sidestepped the central tenet of an <a href="https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/2025-03-26-Letter-to-Hageman-Lummis-Barrasso-With-Signatures.pdf">open letter signed by more than 100 Wyoming lawyers and retired judges</a> and published late last month. <a href="https://wyofile.com/condemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation/">That letter had called on Hageman, Barrasso and Lummis</a> to condemn an increase in personal attacks and calls for impeachment led by the president and his allies on federal judges who issue court decisions they dislike.</p>



<p>The Wyoming jurists who signed that missive focused on Trump’s calls to impeach specific judges who ruled against his policies, and social media posts by Musk calling a judge’s ruling an “attempted coup,” among other criticisms.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The letter also cited threats of violence against judges, a phenomenon U.S. Supreme Court Chief Justice John Roberts has said is on the rise. It also noted Trump’s efforts to target law firms he doesn’t like. “These attacks are part of a growing effort to discredit, not just judges, but seemingly the American Rule of Law,” the letter stated.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The delegation’s response does not mention the president, Musk or threats of violence against judges.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Instead, Barrasso, Lummis and Hageman wrote that “the country is witnessing a healthy debate right now about the appropriate role of judges,” according to a copy of the letter obtained by WyoFile. The federal lawmakers also cited legislation they were cosponsoring to eliminate judges’ authority to issue nationwide injunctions on actions by the federal government.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I think the delegation sort of missed the point,” former Wyoming governor and longtime attorney Mike Sullivan told WyoFile on Monday. “This was not a partisan effort. This is a legitimate, serious and what I think is a constitutional concern about the judiciary and the rule of law.”</p>



<p>Last week, House Republicans including Hageman passed the No Rogue Rulings Act, which would curb judges’ ability to issue nationwide injunctions. Republican lawmakers did so in response to a series of court rulings against aspects of Trump’s agenda — particularly elements of his mass deportation effort that judges found could violate peoples’ civil rights, and parts of the Musk-driven effort to cut budgets and staffing levels across the federal government. Sen. Chuck Grassley, R-Iowa, has introduced a similar measure in the Senate.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="520" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-33.jpg?resize=780%2C520&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-112213" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-33.jpg?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-33.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-33.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-33.jpg?resize=400%2C267&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-33.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/3.19.25-Wyofile-Hageman-Townhall-33-1024x683.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">U.S. Rep. Harriet Hageman, R-Wyo., leans forward to listen to a member of the crowd attending her town hall event on March 19, 2025, in Laramie. (Megan Johnson/WyoFile)</figcaption></figure>



<p>“Both the legislative and the executive branches are rightfully using their constitutional checks and balances to address judicial overreach,” Hageman, Barrasso and Lummis wrote in their letter.</p>



<p>In their letter, the Wyoming jurists told Lummis, Barrasso and Hageman the U.S. Constitution called on them to defend the judiciary from attacks, even if those attacks come from other branches of government.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“As our elected federal representatives—and as required by your own oaths—we thus urge you to publicly condemn these threats, affirm judicial independence, and remind Americans that appeals—not violence, intimidation, or invitations to lawlessness—are the constitutional remedy for undesired court decisions,” the letter read.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Though the delegation in its letter described a bipartisan drive for judicial reform, the No Rogue Rulings Act did not draw any support from Democrats in the House and will likely die in the Senate, where it won’t be able to garner 60 votes, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/04/09/congress/house-passes-national-injunction-bill-00282914">according to a report in Politico</a>.</p>



<p>Lummis, Barrasso and Hageman expressed pique at the letter authors’ choice of an open letter. Among the letter’s more noted signees were former Gov. Mike Sullivan; retired Wyoming Supreme Court Chief Justices Marilyn Kite, Michael Golden, Michael Davis and E. James Burke; retired U.S. District Court Chief Judge William Downes and former Wyoming Attorneys General Gay Woodhouse and Patrick Crank.&nbsp;</p>



<p>(<a href="https://wyofile.com/about/board/">WyoFile board</a> member<a href="https://wyofile.com/i-signed-the-letter-urging-our-congressional-delegation-to-support-the-rule-of-law-heres-why/"> Susan Stubson also signed on</a>. She was not involved in the production of this report, and neither she nor any member of the WyoFile board have <a href="https://wyofile.com/about/operations/code-ethics-2/">authority to direct news coverage or news content</a>.)</p>



<p>Many of those attorneys are retired from public office and working in private practice, if not retired entirely. The jurists appear to have sought a public discussion, concluding their letter with: “We welcome your earliest public response to these very serious concerns.”</p>



<p>But the federal delegates said the more than 100 signees should have reached out as individuals.</p>



<p>“We are disappointed you failed to express your concerns with us directly before rushing to publish your letter,” they wrote. “A robust discussion about addressing the challenges and concerns facing our nation would be more beneficial than attempting to score political points through the press.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>WyoFile reached out to signees of the original letter but did not receive a comment on the delegation’s response by early Monday afternoon. This story will be updated if that changes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Sullivan noted that the Wyoming attorneys published their letter in the wake of a highly unusual statement by Chief Justice Roberts, who protested Trump’s call for the impeachment of U.S. District Judge James E. Boasberg. Trump called for Boasberg’s impeachment after the judge issued a ruling momentarily halting one of Trump’s most controversial deportation policies. Judges are not politicians, Sullivan said, “and when they come down in a way that doesn’t agree with your position they shouldn’t be demeaned or defamed or threatened with impeachment.”</p>



<p>Those signing the letter have an obligation to maintain judicial independence, as does the delegation, the former governor said.</p>



<p>“This is a group that believes this ought to be a public discussion,” Sullivan said. “We have our own constitutional obligations as members of the bar, practicing before the judiciary, and we shouldn’t just sit back and let this happen.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/called-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem/">Called on to defend the rule of law, Wyoming’s delegation says judges, not Trump, are the problem</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/called-on-to-defend-the-rule-of-law-wyomings-delegation-says-judges-not-trump-are-the-problem/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>62</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">113086</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Latest Wyoming abortion law challenge gets a hearing — and a new judge</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/latest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/latest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joshua Wolfson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 21:04:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Legislature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[abortion]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=112716</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="225" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1176&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1500&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="768" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1176&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1500&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>Abortion providers sought an emergency hearing nearly five weeks ago to block new restrictions. That hearing is now set before the third judge assigned to the case.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/latest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge/">Latest Wyoming abortion law challenge gets a hearing — and a new judge</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="225" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1176&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1500&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?fit=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="768" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?w=2560&amp;ssl=1 2560w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1176&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1500&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5950-scaled.jpg?fit=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Flatest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge%2F&amp;linkname=Latest%20Wyoming%20abortion%20law%20challenge%20gets%20a%20hearing%20%E2%80%94%C2%A0and%20a%20new%20judge" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Flatest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge%2F&amp;linkname=Latest%20Wyoming%20abortion%20law%20challenge%20gets%20a%20hearing%20%E2%80%94%C2%A0and%20a%20new%20judge" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Flatest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge%2F&amp;linkname=Latest%20Wyoming%20abortion%20law%20challenge%20gets%20a%20hearing%20%E2%80%94%C2%A0and%20a%20new%20judge" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Flatest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge%2F&amp;linkname=Latest%20Wyoming%20abortion%20law%20challenge%20gets%20a%20hearing%20%E2%80%94%C2%A0and%20a%20new%20judge" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Flatest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge%2F&amp;linkname=Latest%20Wyoming%20abortion%20law%20challenge%20gets%20a%20hearing%20%E2%80%94%C2%A0and%20a%20new%20judge" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Flatest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge%2F&#038;title=Latest%20Wyoming%20abortion%20law%20challenge%20gets%20a%20hearing%20%E2%80%94%C2%A0and%20a%20new%20judge" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/latest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge/" data-a2a-title="Latest Wyoming abortion law challenge gets a hearing — and a new judge"></a></p>
<p>Nearly five weeks ago, lawyers representing Wyoming’s abortion providers sought an emergency court hearing to temporarily halt new restrictions that have effectively shut down Wyoming’s only abortion clinic.</p>



<p>That hearing has finally been set for next week. And when it happens, a new judge will oversee matters — the third jurist assigned to the case since it was first filed Feb. 28.</p>



<p>Documents filed last week in Natrona County District Court show the case is now assigned to a judge who retired from the bench last year: Thomas T.C. Campbell. The documents do not indicate a reason for the change, beyond stating that “good cause exists to assign [the case] to another judge to preside over all further proceedings.”</p>



<p>Before his retirement, Campbell had served as a <a href="https://capcity.news/community/2024/03/15/judge-thomas-campbell-retires-leaves-legacy-of-fairness-and-doing-the-right-thing/">district court judge in Laramie County</a>. He will take over a case that was twice assigned to Natrona County District Judge Dan Forgey and once to Teton County District Judge Melissa Owens.</p>



<p>Opponents of Wyoming’s two recently passed abortion laws <a href="https://wyofile.com/abortion-clinic-files-lawsuit-to-block-new-wyoming-laws/">filed suit</a> at the end of February in Natrona County District Court. They asked Forgey to pause enforcement of both laws — one instituted more regulations on clinics and the second <a href="https://wyofile.com/senate-overrides-gordons-veto-of-abortion-bill-requiring-transvaginal-ultrasounds-in-wyoming/">mandated ultrasounds and a 48-hour waiting period</a> — while the lawsuit proceeds.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="507" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2.jpg?resize=780%2C507&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-112419" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C665&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C195&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C499&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C998&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1330&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C780&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1019&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1299&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C260&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/20250321-abortion-hearing-2-1024x665.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Marci Bramlet, an attorney representing the plaintiffs suing the state, addresses 9th District Court Judge Melissa Owens during a March 2025 hearing in the district court. (Kathryn Ziesig/Jackson Hole News&#038;Guide/pool)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Plaintiffs sought an emergency hearing and temporary restraining order, saying the more onerous regulations that came with requiring abortion clinics to be <a href="https://wyofile.com/wyoming-enacts-new-abortion-clinic-rules-raising-questions-about-casper-facilitys-future/">licensed as ambulatory surgical centers</a> forced the state’s lone facility — Wellspring Health Access in Casper — to stop offering services. In the first five business days after the law went into effect, the clinic said it referred 56 patients to other facilities for abortion-related care.</p>



<p>The plaintiffs say Forgey did not respond to their emergency request in a timely manner, prompting them to refile a nearly identical case in Teton County. While Natrona County is home to Wellspring, patients in Teton County use the clinic’s services, but have been turned away since the new laws went into effect, according to a lawyer for the plaintiffs.</p>



<p>When the case moved to Teton County, it landed before Owens, who had presided over a legal challenge by the same group of plaintiffs to a pair of abortion bans passed by the Wyoming Legislature in 2023. Owens in November <a href="https://wyofile.com/judge-strikes-down-wyoming-abortion-bans/">ruled those bans violated the state constitution</a>, and that case is now before the Wyoming Supreme Court.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="666" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931.jpg?resize=780%2C666&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-111302" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C874&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C256&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C656&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1311&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1748&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1339&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=2000%2C1707&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C341&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/IMG_5931-1024x874.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Wellspring Health Access is pictured in February 2025 in central Casper. It is the only facility to provide in-clinic abortion services. (Joshua Wolfson/WyoFile)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Attorneys for the state, who are tasked with defending the new abortion laws, challenged the move to Teton County, <a href="https://wyofile.com/judge-dismisses-suit-against-wyomings-new-anti-abortion-laws/">saying it amounted to “forum shopping,”</a> the practice of filing a case with a court that a litigant believes will be more favorable to them. They also said Forgey couldn’t schedule the emergency hearing until he received proof that the defendants had been properly served.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In a hearing last month, Owens concluded the latest case belongs in Natrona County, where the lone clinic affected by the new laws operates. The plaintiffs quickly refiled the case there, where it was assigned again to Forgey on March 24, court records show. The following day, Wyoming Supreme Court Chief Justice Kate Fox requested the case be assigned to Campbell. That request did not explain the reassignment or why an outside judge was needed. Beside Forgey, three other district judges serve in Natrona County.</p>





<p>A hearing on whether to pause enforcement of the new abortion laws is now set for April 8 at the state courthouse in downtown Casper. Lawyers for the abortion providers say those laws — like the bans passed in 2023 — violate Wyomingites’ constitutional right to make their own health care decisions.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/latest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge/">Latest Wyoming abortion law challenge gets a hearing — and a new judge</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/latest-wyoming-abortion-law-challenge-gets-a-hearing-and-a-new-judge/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">112716</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Condemn attacks on judiciary, Wyoming lawyers and judges urge delegation</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/condemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/condemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joshua Wolfson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 19:55:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=112520</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="205" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?fit=300%2C205&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=300%2C205&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=1024%2C698&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=768%2C524&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=400%2C273&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?fit=300%2C205&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="698" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?fit=1024%2C698&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=300%2C205&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=1024%2C698&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=768%2C524&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=400%2C273&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?fit=1024%2C698&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>More than 100 members of the state’s legal community, including four retired Supreme Court justices, implored Sens. Barrasso and Lummis and Rep. Hageman to resist “reckless disdain” for the courts.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/condemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation/">Condemn attacks on judiciary, Wyoming lawyers and judges urge delegation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="205" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?fit=300%2C205&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=300%2C205&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=1024%2C698&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=768%2C524&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=400%2C273&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?fit=300%2C205&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="698" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?fit=1024%2C698&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=300%2C205&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=1024%2C698&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=768%2C524&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?resize=400%2C273&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Wyo-Supreme-Court-state-v-counties-Andrew-Graham.jpeg?fit=1024%2C698&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcondemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation%2F&amp;linkname=Condemn%20attacks%20on%20judiciary%2C%20Wyoming%20lawyers%20and%20judges%20urge%20delegation" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcondemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation%2F&amp;linkname=Condemn%20attacks%20on%20judiciary%2C%20Wyoming%20lawyers%20and%20judges%20urge%20delegation" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcondemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation%2F&amp;linkname=Condemn%20attacks%20on%20judiciary%2C%20Wyoming%20lawyers%20and%20judges%20urge%20delegation" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcondemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation%2F&amp;linkname=Condemn%20attacks%20on%20judiciary%2C%20Wyoming%20lawyers%20and%20judges%20urge%20delegation" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcondemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation%2F&amp;linkname=Condemn%20attacks%20on%20judiciary%2C%20Wyoming%20lawyers%20and%20judges%20urge%20delegation" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcondemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation%2F&#038;title=Condemn%20attacks%20on%20judiciary%2C%20Wyoming%20lawyers%20and%20judges%20urge%20delegation" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/condemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation/" data-a2a-title="Condemn attacks on judiciary, Wyoming lawyers and judges urge delegation"></a></p>
<p>A group of more than 100 Wyoming lawyers and retired judges this week urged the state’s congressional delegation to condemn escalating attacks on the judicial branch and its independence by President Donald Trump and his allies.</p>



<p><a href="https://wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/2025-03-26-Letter-to-Hageman-Lummis-Barrasso-With-Signatures.pdf">Writing in an open letter</a> delivered Wednesday to the delegation, the legal professionals cited a chorus of criticism and threats against judges and judicial authority that’s crescendoed through the first two months of the Trump administration, as the president has sought to assert more power over the federal government while dramatically remaking federal agencies through cuts and layoffs.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Specifically, the letter cited Trump’s calls to impeach a judge he deemed a “Radical Left Lunatic,” billionaire Elon Musk’s repeated use of his social media platform X (formerly known as Twitter) to attack court rulings he’s called “evil” and “an attempted coup,” and social media users who’ve even called for judges to be beheaded or hanged.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="585" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=780%2C585&#038;ssl=1" alt="The Wyoming Supreme Court building in Cheyenne at sunset" class="wp-image-91593" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?resize=1568%2C1176&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a.jpeg?w=2048&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5CB9DE32-1190-462D-8882-BE52F396D24A_1_102_a-1024x768.jpeg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The Wyoming Supreme Court in September 2023 in Cheyenne. (Joshua Wolfson/WyoFile)</figcaption></figure>



<p>“The judiciary lacks the Executive&#8217;s bully pulpit or the Legislature&#8217;s power to defend itself. It does not have its own social media platform. Judges are not permitted to publicly discuss their decisions. The Judicial Branch must therefore rely on the other branches of government to respect and defend its constitutional role,” states the letter, which was addressed to Sens. John Barrasso and Cynthia Lummis and Rep. Harriet Hageman. “We do not see that happening.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“As our elected federal representatives— and as required by your own oaths—we thus urge you to publicly condemn these threats, affirm judicial independence, and remind Americans that appeals—not violence, intimidation, or invitations to lawlessness—are the constitutional remedy for undesired court decisions.”</p>



<p>Attacks on the judiciary haven’t been limited to public statements and social media posts, the signees wrote. They noted that some Republicans in the House of Representatives have filed articles of impeachment against federal judges. As of earlier this week, GOP lawmakers had pursued impeachment against six judges who’d ruled against the Trump administration in court, <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/republicans-seek-impeachment-2-more-judges-who-stymied-trump-2025-03-24/">according to a count by Reuters</a>.</p>



<p>Those and other threats, the signers went on to write, are part of an effort not to discredit judges alone, but the rule of law.</p>



<p>“We understand there is an appetite among sizeable members of the electorate for radical change at any cost, but the growing reckless disdain for the independence and security of our judiciary must be resisted by anyone sworn to uphold our Constitution,” the letter reads. “That includes us, and it certainly includes you. Silence in the face of such threats from those with a duty to uphold the Constitution will be properly seen as complicity.”</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="585" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?resize=780%2C585&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-109366" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop.jpg?w=1200&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/supremecourtcrop-1024x768.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The Wyoming Supreme Court building in Cheyenne inscribed with the phrase &#8220;equality before the law.&#8221; (Mike Vanata/WyoFile) </figcaption></figure>



<p>The letter signees include former Gov. Mike Sullivan; retired Wyoming Supreme Court Chief Justices Marilyn Kite, Michael Golden, Michael Davis and E. James Burke; retired U.S. District Court Chief Judge William Downes and former Wyoming Attorneys General Gay Woodhouse and Patrick Crank.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The letter signers hope the delegation will be “allies” in upholding the constitutional structure central to the nation’s democracy, retired state district judge Tim Day told WyoFile.</p>



<p>“We really hope that our congressional delegation will do the same, and that they won’t sit on their hands, and they will identify these as dangerous actions and dangerous words.”&nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Motivations for signing </strong></h4>



<p>The letter is not political, and it aims to ensure the courts remain independent of political influence, Day said. Undermining the independence of the judiciary, disregarding legal decisions and not defending the separation of powers paves the way for oppression, he warned.</p>



<p>The U.S. Constitution anticipated such threats, he noted.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“It&#8217;s exactly the kind of thing that our founding fathers put in the first three articles of the Constitution because of what happened with the colonies with England,” Day said. “They were oppressed. So they didn’t want that to happen again.</p>



<p>“We&#8217;re asking our congressional delegation, two of whom are lawyers, to acknowledge that these are basic foundational tenants in our Constitution, critical to our democracy and the proper functioning of our government, with separation of powers and checks and balances.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Sullivan, a lawyer who served two terms as Wyoming’s governor, also hopes the delegation will “recognize the need to step up and respond.” He said his decision to sign the letter reflects &#8220;a concern about the administration&#8217;s policy on the rule of law and judges and lawyers and matters associated with the rule of law, and I thought it reflected well upon the concerns, and was happy to sign it.&#8221;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="520" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000.jpg?resize=780%2C520&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-51011" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000.jpg?w=1024&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000.jpg?resize=450%2C300&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000.jpg?resize=728%2C486&amp;ssl=1 728w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000.jpg?resize=745%2C497&amp;ssl=1 745w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000-1024x683.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/USSupremeCourtEnviosFlickrcc1000-1024x683.jpg?w=400&amp;ssl=1 400w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The United States Supreme Court. (Envios / Flickr Creative Commons)</figcaption></figure>



<p>After Trump called for the impeachment of U.S. District Judge James E. Boasberg for issuing an order that sought to halt deportation flights, U.S. Supreme Court Chief Justice John Roberts issued a rare public statement. In it, Roberts stressed that two centuries of precedent have established that “impeachment is not an appropriate response to disagreement concerning a judicial decision.” That proper response, he added, was the normal appellate process.</p>



<p>American governance, as envisioned by the country&#8217;s founders, relies on respecting the judiciary as being just as critical to a healthy democracy as the other two branches of government, explained Kite, who served on the Wyoming Supreme Court for 15 years, including four as chief justice.</p>



<p>If you undo the Constitution just to get things done, you no longer have a free and open democratic society, she said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“The rule of law isn’t what you want it to be,” Kite said. “It is what is established in the laws, and the laws are interpreted by the courts, and that’s been the case for 250 years.”</p>



<p>When asked about his motivations for signing the letter, Kite’s former colleague on the state’s high court, Michael Golden, recalled his decades practicing law, including four years in the Judge Advocate General’s Office and another 24 on the Wyoming Supreme Court. Golden said he believed strongly in the state and federal constitutions, along with the rule of law, and was alarmed by actions now taking place in Washington.</p>



<p>“If we lose respect [for] our courts, if we lose sight of the rule of law and our Constitution, then that will be what destroys our country,” he told WyoFile. “And that just speaks to the very heart of what we’re concerned about.”</p>



<p>Retired state district judge Peter Arnold was more blunt about his motivations for speaking out — and whether it will influence Wyoming’s congressional delegation.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="545" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3.jpg?resize=780%2C545&#038;ssl=1" alt="A crowded courtroom" class="wp-image-93423" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=1024%2C715&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=300%2C209&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=768%2C536&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=1536%2C1072&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=2048%2C1429&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=1200%2C837&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=1568%2C1094&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=400%2C279&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?resize=706%2C493&amp;ssl=1 706w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-scaled.jpg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/summary-judgment-hearing-3-1024x715.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jay Jerde, special assistant attorney general for the state, addresses 9th Judicial District Court Judge Melissa Owens during a summary judgment hearing in Teton County District Court. (Kathryn Ziesig/Jackson Hole News &amp; Guide)</figcaption></figure>



<p>“I signed the letter about which you contacted me because I strongly disagree that it is proper to speak about judges the way Trump is,” he wrote in an email to WyoFile. “I am not naive, I understand the pressures faced by our legislators and doubt the letter will do much good but I would be remiss if I didn&#8217;t express my beliefs publicly to our legislators.</p>



<p>“In my mind, Congress has a constitutional responsibility to publicly disagree with Trump,” wrote Arnold, a Republican who served on the Laramie County GOP General Committee and who was censured by the panel for raising the same issues. “Again, it is naive for me to expect much but to do nothing is not an option.”</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Congressional delegation</strong></h4>



<p>WyoFile emailed questions about the letter to Barrasso, Lummis and Hageman early Wednesday evening. As of publication time Thursday afternoon, none had responded.</p>



<p>But in previous comments, speeches and letters, the lawmakers gave some insight into their views on the recent attacks on judges.&nbsp;</p>



<p>On Feb. 10, for example, the delegation held a tele-town hall and were asked about what Republicans could do to stop Democrats and judges from blocking parts of Trump’s agenda.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="515" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=780%2C515&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-112518" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1024%2C676&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=768%2C507&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=1200%2C792&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?resize=400%2C264&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall.jpg?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/tele-town-hall-1024x676.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Rep. Harriet Hageman, left, Sen. Cynthia Lummis, middle, and Sen. John Barrasso participate in a tele-town hall on Feb. 10. (Sen. John Barrasso/Facebook)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Hageman, a lawyer herself, accused judges of “clearly acting politically” and suggested the administration expedite appeals or even outright ignore judges.</p>



<p>“When you have a judge who issues the decision saying that the Secretary of the Treasury is not allowed to access the documents of the Treasury, you&#8217;ve got a rogue judge,” Hageman said. “And I think that you may see the House moving forward with some ideas of what we&#8217;re going to do in that regard.</p>



<p>“One of the things that I think is going to happen, and what this administration needs to do, is really work to expedite the appeals on these absolutely outrageous decisions. It&#8217;s another form of lawfare, and it is just another example of how our system was broken with these rogue judges that have been appointed by Obama and Biden especially. They&#8217;re gonna have to go through the process. I wish I had a different answer for you.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I will tell you one thing that I&#8217;d like to consider, if I was the Secretary of Treasury &#8230; I might just say, ‘This is my agency. My responsibility is to take care of these records. I absolutely have to have access to them,’ and dare the judge to hold him in contempt. That&#8217;s what I might consider.”</p>



<p>Hageman went on to say that such a step —&nbsp;disobeying a judge and daring them to hold a person in contempt — is not something she’d normally recommend. But she went on to suggest there were times when it would be necessary to do just that.</p>



<p>“And I just, I think at some point you got to tell these judges, &#8216;You really do not have the power that you think that you do. You want to hold me in contempt of court, have at it, baby.’”</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="578" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/trump-barrasso.jpg?resize=780%2C578&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-112519" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/trump-barrasso.jpg?resize=1024%2C759&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/trump-barrasso.jpg?resize=300%2C222&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/trump-barrasso.jpg?resize=768%2C569&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/trump-barrasso.jpg?resize=1200%2C889&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/trump-barrasso.jpg?resize=400%2C296&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/trump-barrasso.jpg?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/trump-barrasso-1024x759.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">President Donald Trump speaks as Sen. John Barrasso listens in this undated photo posted to the lawmaker&#8217;s Facebook. </figcaption></figure>



<p>More recently, Barrasso took aim at “activist district court judges” in a speech earlier this month from the Senate floor. He accused those judges of “protecting criminals, terrorists and corrupt bureaucrats from the accountability that voters demand.”</p>



<p>“Let me be clear. When partisan, unelected district court judges try to micromanage the president of the United States, it isn’t judicial review,” he said. “It isn’t checks and balances. It is purely partisan politics — and it is wrong. Radical district judges will not succeed in blocking Republicans from getting America back on track.”</p>



<p>Lummis has been publicly supportive of many of Trump’s efforts to downsize the federal government. On Wednesday, Trump endorsed her for reelection.</p>



<p><em>WyoFile editors Tennessee Watson and Rebecca Huntington, along with writer CJ Baker, contributed to this report.&nbsp;</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/condemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation/">Condemn attacks on judiciary, Wyoming lawyers and judges urge delegation</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/condemn-attacks-on-judiciary-wyoming-lawyers-and-judges-urge-delegation/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>40</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">112520</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>‘Come out and tell the truth’: Parents of teen who died outside Riverton wait for answers</title>
		<link>https://wyofile.com/come-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers/</link>
					<comments>https://wyofile.com/come-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andrew Graham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 10:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured Top Story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Latest news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wind River Reservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[domestic violence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FBI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kevin ferris]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[law enforcement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[missing murdered indigenous]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MMIP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mmiw]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stephanie bearstail]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://wyofile.com/?p=112493</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="200" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?w=1400&amp;ssl=1 1400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=400 400w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div>
<figure><img width="1024" height="683" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?w=1400&amp;ssl=1 1400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=400 400w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure>
<p>It’s been three weeks since Stephanie Bearstail died under suspicious circumstances on the Wind River Indian Reservation. Her family mourns as they wait for answers from federal investigators.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/come-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers/">‘Come out and tell the truth’: Parents of teen who died outside Riverton wait for answers</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><img width="300" height="200" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-medium size-medium wp-post-image" alt="" style="margin-bottom: 15px;" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?w=1400&amp;ssl=1 1400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=400 400w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></div><figure><img width="1024" height="683" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1" class="attachment-rss-image-size size-rss-image-size wp-post-image" alt="" decoding="async" loading="lazy" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?w=1400&amp;ssl=1 1400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/StephBearstail-e1743031391980.jpeg?fit=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=400 400w" sizes="(max-width: 34.9rem) calc(100vw - 2rem), (max-width: 53rem) calc(8 * (100vw / 12)), (min-width: 53rem) calc(6 * (100vw / 12)), 100vw" /></figure><p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcome-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers%2F&amp;linkname=%E2%80%98Come%20out%20and%20tell%20the%20truth%E2%80%99%3A%20Parents%20of%20teen%20who%20died%20outside%20Riverton%20wait%20for%20answers" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_bluesky" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/bluesky?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcome-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers%2F&amp;linkname=%E2%80%98Come%20out%20and%20tell%20the%20truth%E2%80%99%3A%20Parents%20of%20teen%20who%20died%20outside%20Riverton%20wait%20for%20answers" title="Bluesky" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_whatsapp" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/whatsapp?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcome-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers%2F&amp;linkname=%E2%80%98Come%20out%20and%20tell%20the%20truth%E2%80%99%3A%20Parents%20of%20teen%20who%20died%20outside%20Riverton%20wait%20for%20answers" title="WhatsApp" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_facebook_messenger" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook_messenger?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcome-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers%2F&amp;linkname=%E2%80%98Come%20out%20and%20tell%20the%20truth%E2%80%99%3A%20Parents%20of%20teen%20who%20died%20outside%20Riverton%20wait%20for%20answers" title="Messenger" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcome-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers%2F&amp;linkname=%E2%80%98Come%20out%20and%20tell%20the%20truth%E2%80%99%3A%20Parents%20of%20teen%20who%20died%20outside%20Riverton%20wait%20for%20answers" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwyofile.com%2Fcome-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers%2F&#038;title=%E2%80%98Come%20out%20and%20tell%20the%20truth%E2%80%99%3A%20Parents%20of%20teen%20who%20died%20outside%20Riverton%20wait%20for%20answers" data-a2a-url="https://wyofile.com/come-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers/" data-a2a-title="‘Come out and tell the truth’: Parents of teen who died outside Riverton wait for answers"></a></p>
<p>It’s been three weeks since Stephanie Bearstail died under suspicious circumstances on the Wind River Indian Reservation, and the 18-year-old’s family is mourning her as they wait for answers from federal investigators.</p>



<p>Bearstail was a passionate softball player and determined student eager to graduate high school and enter college — she had recently expressed interest in becoming a radiologist, her parents Nikki and Kevin Ferris told WyoFile in a phone interview this week. As a senior, she was already taking courses at Central Wyoming College.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Their only daughter was also a certified goofball, a little boss of the house and her three brothers, and a bright light in the lives of the family and many others on the reservation.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Even we were surprised how many people knew her,” Nikki Ferris said. “We knew of her friends, but we didn’t know how many she had.” </p>



<p>On March 15, those friends and others — as many as 200 people, according to news reports — walked to a fence line along the side of Wyoming 137, a road that cuts across the reservation, running from near the Wind River Casino outside Riverton west to Fort Washakie. That’s the area where authorities say Bearstail somehow exited a moving vehicle on a windy March night.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="780" height="592" onerror="if (typeof newspackHandleImageError === 'function') newspackHandleImageError(this);" src="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780.jpeg?resize=780%2C592&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-112501" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=1024%2C777&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=300%2C228&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=768%2C583&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=1536%2C1166&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=2048%2C1554&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=1200%2C911&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=1568%2C1190&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=2000%2C1518&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?resize=400%2C304&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-scaled.jpeg?w=2340&amp;ssl=1 2340w, https://i0.wp.com/wyofile.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/IMG_5780-1024x777.jpeg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">A memorial at a roadside outside Riverton that investigators have connected to the death of Stephanie Bearstail, who is believed to have exited a moving SUV amid circumstances that remain a mystery to the public. (Andrew Graham/WyoFile)</figcaption></figure>



<p>At the demonstration, Bearstail’s supporters wore red — the color that has become a symbol for the issue of missing and murdered indigenous women that plagues communities on and off the reservation. They carried signs that read “Justice for Steph,” some of which still hung weeks later on the barbed wire fence that threads between the sage brush.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Bearstail’s death, her mother said, “just blindsided all of us.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Ferrises declined to share details, saying they do not want to publicly reveal information that could complicate the job of investigators. But they have reason to believe their daughter was a victim of violence, they said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“The main thing that I think of every day is I just wish somebody would come out and tell the truth about what happened,” Nikki said. “I don’t understand how anyone could know what happened and not say anything.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Bearstail grew up and lived her entire life in Fort Washakie, where her father was involved in law enforcement and today is a judge on the Wind River Tribal Court.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The night of March 4, Bearstail did not return home by her 10:30 p.m. curfew. The parents could remember only one other time their lively but studious daughter had been late for her curfew, they told WyoFile. They grew worried, and within an hour, left home to look for her.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The parents tracked their daughter’s phone location, which placed her in the area between Riverton and the small reservation community of Arapahoe. “She did need help, and we were trying to find her,” her mother said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>On the drive, they received word she had been hospitalized, and so they headed to SageWest Hospital in Riverton. They were able to spend time with Bearstail before she died, but their daughter was unable to speak or share what happened to her, they said.</p>



<p>The Wyoming Highway Patrol, which maintains a list of highway fatalities from around the state, published an entry to the list about a week after Bearstail’s death, according to news reports. <a href="https://webapp.dot.state.wy.us/ao/r/fatalities/fatalitycrashinfo/summary?p6_fatality_report_id=1179&amp;session=102174943231873&amp;cs=3TpIKfSikegm-Og9UhPmyXlCQyPQhymXmH6YbioiJ8R7oSezHaXv02Av9I-MwEaBeiOH0GpntQdBnquaU4EWqfA" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The entry states</a>: “An unknown SUV was traveling westbound on Rendezvous Road. The SUV passenger allegedly jumped out of the vehicle while it was in motion for unknown reasons.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>The entry does not say where investigators learned of the allegation that Bearstail jumped from the SUV. Authorities haven’t identified the driver. The Wyoming Highway Patrol directed WyoFile to the FBI for comment on the case. The FBI has said only that the case remains under investigation. The Fremont County Coroner’s office is conducting the autopsy, which hasn’t been finalized, a representative of that office said this week.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Using the limited information from the highway patrol fatality database, news organizations ran headlines stating that Bearstail “allegedly jumped” from the car to her death. Those reports disturbed the family, the Ferrises said, because taken in isolation, the information suggests Bearstail was responsible for her own death.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The headlines, Nikki said, served “to deflect off what happened to her.” But Bearstail’s community appears dedicated to keeping focus on her case and on the issue of domestic violence, which they believe led to her death. Other community events are in the works, the Ferrises told WyoFile.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Native American women fall prey to violence, murders and unexplained deaths at disproportionally higher rates compared to other demographics in the United States.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Many of the cases go unsolved, and reformers have pointed to the complicated jurisdictional nature of reservations — where local, state, federal and tribal law enforcement sometimes overlap in areas that are often economically depressed and, in the West, geographically isolated — as leading to a lack of accountability for perpetrators of violence.</p>



<p>That does not appear to be the case here, as the FBI swiftly took control of the investigation. “In this case, the FBI, they were [at the crime scene] that morning,” Nikki said. “They got involved quickly.”</p>





<p>Bearstail was the second oldest of the couple’s children. Her younger brothers, ages 15 and 13, have tried to return to school, but on some days have had to go home or haven’t been up for going at all, their mother said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“They’re not doing OK,” Nikki said. “It&#8217;s really hard.”</p>



<p>Since her daughter’s death, Nikki has made a steady stream of posts to social media, calling for justice, expressing her raw grief and remembering her daughter. There are videos of Bearstail running track, and of her dancing — full of life.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As the Ferrises have received messages sharing swirling rumors about the night Bearstail died, they’ve implored people to take what they know to the FBI. But to date, all the family has been told by officials is that an investigation is active, the parents said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The FBI “said it would take time,” Nikki said in the March 25 interview. To her knowledge, “they’re still out there investigating,” she said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In a statement to WyoFile sent Wednesday evening, an FBI spokesperson for the Denver Field Office said the agency “appreciate[s] public interest in this incident and encourage[s] anyone with information to contact the Bureau of Indian Affairs/Wind River Police or the FBI.”</p>



<p>The agency could not offer a time frame for when it would conclude the investigation, the statement read. “We methodically and thoroughly address every element of the incident,” spokesperson Vikki Migoya said.&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>Correction: This story was updated to correct a misspelling of Nikki Ferris&#8217; name. —Ed.</em></p>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://wyofile.com/come-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers/">‘Come out and tell the truth’: Parents of teen who died outside Riverton wait for answers</a> appeared first on <a href="https://wyofile.com">WyoFile </a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://wyofile.com/come-out-and-tell-the-truth-parents-of-teen-who-died-outside-riverton-wait-for-answers/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">112493</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>